Here, we see an example of an intrusion detection system I DS alert.
This is being provided as an example of how threats are identified.
Some of the concepts in this scenario are more advanced than this course.
So don't be alarmed if you don't understand everything discussed here,
we'll start by reviewing the main points of the data that is presented to us.
Note that in this example,
the host name and user name fields have been removed to maintain anonymity.
This tells us that the I DS detected the use of software called advanced IP scanner
that can be used by Attackers to enumerate or look through the network scanning
addresses to see what services are running on the computers in the local network.
This software is also used by network or system
administrators to inventory a local network for troubleshooting purposes.
Finally,
this top section of the alert screen tells us
that the event was reported by an endpoint agent,
meaning that it was generated by a host intrusion detection system, H I DS solution,
not a network intrusion detection system
N I DS.
This line identifies the host that is running
the suspicious process as a Windows system.
This process section identifies the start time process name and ID or P
ID number that correlates to the process in the Windows task manager.
This can be helpful in a couple of ways.
First, the start time tells us how long the process has been running.
The P ID can also give some clues as lower P
ID numbers may indicate a process that started running during the boot
sequence and higher numbers indicate something that was started much later.
These lines give us the details of the executable file,
including the path to the file itself as well as the
actual command line that was used to run the executable.
These are important contextually as they show the program
executed from a temp folder under the user's id,
which typically does not require administrative privileges in a windows system.
In other words, they could be run by any average user.
The command line used shows additional context including that
the application is running as a portable application,
meaning that it doesn't have to be formally installed on the machine to execute.
In this case,
there is not enough context to really know if
this process is being used in a malicious manner.
Like many security alerts, this one relies on some human interaction.
So you should contact the end user assigned to this asset
to inquire whether they are in fact running this software.
And if they have a legitimate business reason to do so,
if you discover that this was intended.
It might be a good place to explain too that
you were alerted because this legitimate software can be used
by threat actors to conduct reconnaissance on the local network
to determine where there might be weaknesses to exploit.